Edward J. Pettid papers, 1849-1980
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Edward J. Pettid papers, 1849-1980
MS 314
Pettid, Edward J., 1914-
Manuscript draft about the Oatman family massacre in 1851, also included are research materials and photographs pertaining to the draft and other writings about the Southwest by the author during the 1960s. Research materials include photocopies of correspondence and documents from the Oatman family, friends, and Ft. Yuma personnel relating to the massacre, and events from the later years.
.2 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Administrative Information
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Father Edward J. Pettid, S.J., was born in Phoenix, Arizona, in November, 1914. He attended Catholic schools in Phoenix before being ordained in the Jesuit order in 1947. After serving as an army chaplain for three years, he taught high schools in Arizona and California for approximately twenty years.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Manuscript Draft, The Oatman Story, ca. 1969
Series II: Writings, 1968-1980
Series III: Research Materials, 1849-1951
Series IV: Photographs, ca. 1850-1950
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes an unpublished manuscript, other published articles written or edited by E.J. Pettid, research materials and photographs. His main research topic concerned the Oatman family massacre that took place near Yuma, Arizona, in February, 1851, and subsequent events involving the captivity of Mary Ann and Olive Oatman. The manuscript draft, The Oatman Story (ca. 205 pp.), is a photocopy, and includes handwritten notes and editing by Pettid. It was probably written in the 1960s. The location of the original is unknown.
There are seven other articles by him written chiefly about the Oatman tragedy or related persons and events. These articles were written in the late 1960s, and include "Oatman Story: A Frontier Tragedy," "Oatman Letters Returned to El Monte," "Henry Stewart Hewitt, MD."
"The Shaman's Tale of Mohave Creation," and "John Lawrence Le Conte, MD". Research materials ranging from 1849 to 1951 include copies of letters, legal documents, an article and a few of his notes. Among the photographic materials are a few originals, copy prints, and some negatives. There are portraits and snapshots of various Oatman family, members including Olive and her husband, John Fairchild; of E.J Pettid; and of three unidentified men.
Access Terms
Oatman, Olive Ann
Oatman family
Indian captivities
Arizona -- History -- To 1912
Correspondence
Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Manuscript Draft, The Oatman Story, ca. 1969
  Typescript (photocopy), some handwritten notes.
  - Pages 1-61. ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pages 62-158. ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pages 159-205. ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Writings, 1968-1980
  Seven articles and items written or edited by Pettid. Three photographs of Henry Hewitt and John Le Conte (some negatives) filed in Photographs series.
  - Writings, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes:
    "The Oatman Story: A Frontier Tragedy." Arizona Highways, XLVI:11 (Nov. 1968): 4-9.
    "Olive Ann Oatman's Lecture Notes and the Oatman Bibliography." San Bernardino County Museum Association Quarterly, XVI:2 Winter, 1968.
    "Oatman Letters Returned to El Monte." The Landmark, El Monte Historical Society, 4:2 (Jan. 1969). 2 copies.
  - Writings, 1969-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Henry Stewart Hewitt." Arizona Medicine, 26:1 (Jan.1969): 62- 70.
    "The Shaman's Tale of the Mohave Creation." Northern Yavapai Record, Jan. 10, 1969: 4.
    "John Lawrence Le Conte, M.D." Arizona Medicine, 33:10 (Oct. 1976): 843-845 (pt. 1 of 2).
    "John Lawrence Le Conte, M.D." Arizona Medicine, 33:11 (Nov. 1976): 956-959 (pt. 2 of 2).
    "The Inland California Missions," remarks at celebration of Saint Thomas Mission, Fort Yuma, bicentennial, Nov. 23, 1980. 2 pages.
- Series III: Research Materials, 1849-1951
  Photocopies of letters, documents, and original notes.
  - Research Materials, 1849-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Land ownership document of Oatman's, from Illinois, 1849.
    Letter from commander of Ft. Yuma, 1852, to Oatman relative, in response to inquiry about Oatman family.
    Adoption paper of Sarah Catherine Leonard, adopted by Olive and John Fairchild in 1876.
    Olive Oatman to relatives, 1858-1889.
    Lorenzo Oatman (brother) to relatives, 1852-1858.
    John B. Fairchild, 1879-1889.
    Others, 1850's-1866.
    Olive Oatman's Return," by A. L. Kroeber. Kroeber Anthropological Society Papers, No. 4, Berkeley, 1951.
    E.J. Pettid's list of tasks. No Date
    E.J. Pettid's registered envelope. No Date
- Series IV: Photographs, ca. 1851-1960
  25 photographs, 5 sets of negatives.
  - Photographs ca. 1851-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    E.J. Pettid. ca. 1960
    Negatives, 35mm. No Date
    Insignias of original photographers. No Date
    Family: (copies of photographs, and a few originals) of Olive Oatman, John B. Fairchild, various family members (including their adopted daughter), ca. 1850-1924.
    Miscellaneous: includes the Fairchild home in Sherman, Texas; grave headstones of Olive and John B. Fairchild; J.W. Strode and G.W.P. Hunt at Arizona grave site, 1927; and a color photograph of a beaded handbag made by Olive Oatman. 1927, No Date
    Three unidentified men. No Date
    Three photographs, one of Dr. Hewitt and two of Dr. Le Conte, with negatives. No Date